Guide to the N. Scott Momaday Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
N. Scott Momaday papers
1788-2012
1950-2012
YCAL MSS 807
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
72.93
125 boxes + 3 art, 15 broadside, 2 record album storage, 1 roll
Momaday, N. Scott, 1934-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Ken Lopez Bookseller on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 21, 27, 30, 40, 45, 46, 42, 80, 87-89, 147 (audiovisual materials): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 106-107 (digital media): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
N. Scott Momaday
N. Scott Momaday (b. 1934) is a Native American writer, painter, and activist of Kiowa descent. His mother, Natachee Scott Momaday, taught elementary school in the Navajo Nation. His father, Al Momaday, was a painter.
Momaday has written 17 books of fiction, poetry, drama and history. His novel House Made of Dawn received rhe Pulitzer Prize for Fiction in 1969. Momaday is the founder of the Rainy Mountain Foundation and Buffalo Trust, a nonprofit organization working to preserve Native American cultures.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Papers, 1788-2012. II. Audiovisual Materials, 1965-2009. III. Electronic Media, 2002-2012.
American literature -- 20th Century; American literature -- Indian authors; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Sound recordings; Momaday, N. Scott, 1934-
- Papers, 1788-2012; 1950s-2012
  Arrangement
  Arranged in the order in which the materials were recieved.
  - Zaldivar and the Cattle of Cibola; Edited Spanish Texts (Book), undated (Box 1)
  - Misc. photocopies of poems and prayers by NSM; Class rosters from 2003; Letters and emails to NSM from around 2003; Color photographs from "France Culture" event., circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of Bill and Libby Hicks Music CD sleeve with an email about the CD from Mark Gordon Allen, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Fortune Magazine (Dec.3 2001) featuring NSM on page 126., circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Speech/story, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Misc. letters to NSM, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Information on NSM trip to Lewis and Clark College (2004), circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Letters to and from NSM (Early 2000s), circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of poems and writings by NSM, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Publications and photocopies of works by others; including poems by John Ridland, "Crossing the Arctic Circle with Raven" by Susan Scarberry-Garcia, and "Planet of weeds" by David Quammen., circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - "The Indolent Boys" by NSM Manuscript of a play, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Misc. photocopies of writings by NSM; email correspondence to and from NSM, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Research on Charles Manson, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings; handwritten notes and ideas by NSM, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of "A Dark, Indifferent Rage" a novel by NSM, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Information regarding an appearance on KUNM, the University of New Mexico radio station, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts and writings by NSM, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Misc. letters and emails to NSM and Barbara Glenn Momaday circa 2004, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts and writings by NSM including a back up computer floppy disc of work, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts and writings by NSM (the second group of hard copies located on the disc in folder (1):19), circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts and writings by NSM including a back up computer floppy disc of work, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Information and programs from The University of Oklahoma when they awarded NSM an honorary degree, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Paperwork from the International Achievement Summit 2004, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Information and correspondence regarding "Ancient Roots: Modern Medicine" which NSM narrated at least parts of. The Disc of the episode is included., circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Misc. correspondence and papers, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Information on NSM Honorary degree from Clermont-Ferrand, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Speaking arrangements and book signing at Palais des Congress de Montreal, Canada, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Travel and speaking arrangements for NSM to speak in St. Louis, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - Misc. cards and pamphlets, circa 2000s (Box 1)
  - University of Oklahoma Commencement booklet, 2004 from NSM honorary degree, circa 2000s (Box 1)
    Separated Materials
    One video cassette and one audiocassette removed to Box 147.
  - Misc. periodicals from the 1970s and 1980s, circa 1970s (Box 1)
  - Misc. papers and letters from the 1970s. Some to NSM others to Al and Natachee S. Momaday, circa 1970s (Box 1)
  - Misc. periodicals and papers from the 1970s. Appear to belong to Natachee S. Momaday, circa 1970s (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings of stories on NSM and Natachee S. Momaday, undated (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of newspaper clippings c. 1993, circa 1990s (Box 1)
  - NSM CV c. 1993, circa 1990s (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts by NSM, undated (Box 1)
  - Folder with prints of Al Momaday's work for a show at the Philbrook Museum of Art, undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts and misc. writings by NSM, undated (Box 2)
  - Manuscript of The Cambridge Companion to Native American Literature, with a letter asking for NSM comments (Part 1), undated (Box 2)
  - Manuscript of The Cambridge Companion to Native American Literature, with a letter asking for NSM comments (Part 2), undated (Box 2)
  - Booklets and journals: Heard Museum History and Collections Ann Marshall, Mary Brennan and Nicole Haas (2006); Voices Heard (2009); Earthsong (Feb-March 2010 & April-June 2010); Ordering sheet for NSM: Remembering Ancestors, Earth, and Traditions: An Annotated Bio-bibliography by Phyllis S. Morgan (University of Oklahoma Press); Margaret Wood Ballad; Print out of Ted Roethke poems; University of Illinois at Chicago Commencement book, May 2010 (NSM received an honorary degree)., circa 2010s (Box 2)
  - Folder of Heard Library Materials from 2009-2010, including staff and facility information, photographs of the library and sample repository guides., circa 2010s (Box 2)
  - Manuscript: Weaving Life Stories: Healing Selves in Native American Autobiographical Narratives, by Narta Ramos Oliveira (2009) containing some of NSM work; A note from Pearson publishing regarding the right to reproduce a section from "The Names" by NSM; Article from Taos Magazine, "The Message in the Medium" by Stephen M. Parks (2009)., circa 2000s (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts by NSM: Granada: A Vision of the Unforeseen (2 copies), The American West and the Burden of Belief; Poem: "To An Aged Bear" and an unnamed poem., undated (Box 2)
  - Manuscript of The Man Made of Words by NSM, undated (Box 2)
  - Writings by NSM: "Names and Beings", Speech and presentation (appears to be on The House Made of Dawn), Tsoai and the Shieldmaker, Handwritten notes on Tsaoi, Speech on the character of the Southwest, and a few unnamed writings and prayers, undated (Box 2)
  - Writings by NSM: The American West and the Burden of Belief (Author's copy of what publication will look like), The American West and the Burden of Belief manuscript, Again The Far Morning manuscript, undated (Box 2)
  - Again The Far Morning manuscript by NSM, circa 2010s (Box 2)
  - Writings by NSM: When Dogs Could Talk manuscript, A number of lose poems, Card and empty mailing envelope from P. Anne Greenwood, Requests to reprint NSM work, "NSM et Laure Morali" letter exchanges, misc. papers concerning writings, poster announcements of presentations and readings, and email correspondence regarding publications and appearances., undated (Box 2)
  - Request from Bedford/St. Martin to reprint material, Letter to "Bear" from "Butterfly", Thank you note from the American Academy of Pediatrics for hi presentation, The Stories: A Memoir, manuscript by NSM, The Stories map, "An Honor Song for the President, Death insurance papers, Misc. poems, Letter to "Butterfly" from "Bear"., undated (Box 2)
  - Newspaper article on boarding schools, photocopies of "The Red Man and Helper" commemorative issue, A script of dialogue, Showtime letter and pay stub, handwritten notes, undated (Box 2)
  - One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest screenplay (1974), circa 1970s (Box 2)
  - List of author's and their works including Emily Dickinson, Walt Whitman, Frederick Goddard Tuckerman, Robert Frost, Wallace Stevens, William Carlos Williams, Hart Crane, Yvor Winters, undated (Box 2)
  - Black Hills Hallucinations by Bernard Pomerance, manuscript, undated (Box 2)
  - Theater: Featuring Bernard Pomerance's New Play, MELONS, (Spring 1988), circa 1980s (Box 2)
  - One Day in the World of My Brilliant Mind: A Minor Classic by Bobby Jack Nelson, undated (Box 2)
  - Hands of Light by Bernard Pomerance manuscript, undated (Box 2)
  - Silence of the Lamb screenplay (1989), circa 1980s (Box 2)
  - Printout of Phyllis Morgan's manuscript "NSM: Remembering Ancestors, Earth, and Traditions: A Bio-bibliography"., undated (Box 2)
  - Children of the Sun: A Play by NSM manuscript (4 copies), undated (Box 3)
  - Children of the Sun: A Play by NSM manuscript (4 copies), undated (Box 3)
  - To Honor the Gift by NSM manuscript with handwritten notes and poems attached., undated (Box 3)
  - A Memoir for his wife, Barbara, Misc. poems at various stages of development by NSM, Photographs of him presenting at the Oklahoma History Center, undated (Box 3)
  - Various poems as different stages of development, Email correspondence with Stacia Spragg, financial documents, undated (Box 3)
  - Various poems at different stages of development, Edited copy of The Way of Kinship with note from the editor, Louisa Castner (2010), Royalty statement for period ending March 2010, Collected Works Bookstore inquiry about an appearance, Email correspondence, Poems from poetry students., circa 2010s (Box 3)
  - Various writings and poetry at different stages of development, FedEx shipping labels, Letter from Houghton Mifflin Harcourt to requesting the rights to reprint "The Delight song of Tsoai-tale", undated (Box 3)
  - Requests for the rights to reprint material, Various poems including "I Would Take You There", "The Story of Light", "Canyon Time", "Death Comes for Beowulf", "The Wheel", "Oklahoma Seasonal"; Many "Get-well" notes to NSM with donations, Royalty check stubs, email correspondence., undated (Box 3)
  - Emails, notes, and information for a Human Dignity Meeting (2007?), circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Email correspondence regarding a Regional Conference on Literacy (2007), circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Two copies of The Alphabet of Hope a UNESCO publication to which NSM contributed. One copy is in English, the other in Spanish with a note from the publisher, undated (Box 3)
  - Email correspondence regarding an appearance and reading at the University of North Texas (2008), circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings of stories on NSM circa. 2007, circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Card from Laura Bush request NSM to come to the White House for the 2007 National Book Festival; The Centennial Issue of Oklahoma Today (2007); Dust Jackets for Three Plays by NSM with a letter from University of Oklahoma Press regarding their design; Newspaper Clippings on NSM (2007; CD-R Disc with no labels; Announcement on NSM induction in the Oklahoma Writers Hall of Fame (2007); Review of Three Plays; Email correspondence regarding appearances and payments, circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Announcement of NSM induction into the Oklahoma Writers Hall of Fame October 23, 2007, circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - National Book Festival memorabilia from 2007; including maps, Identification cards, table assignment cards, itineraries, pamphlets and brochures, circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Information regarding a trip to an event for the National Endowment of the Arts 11/14-11/15 2007. NSM received the National Medal of Arts; the folder includes airline tickets, letters announcing that NSM will be receiving the awards, photographs of the event, media coverage, and other memorabilia from the event., circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Institute on American Indian Arts Foundation (IAIA) thanking NSM for providing a reading at their gala (August 2007); A booklet entitled "An Ancient and Emerging Field: Feasibility Study for a National Native Arts and Culture Fund; A disc probably containing photographs with a note; :Under One Big Sky: Autry National Center 2006 Annual Report"; "School of Advanced Research on the Human Experience: Celebrating a Century Annual Review 2006-2007"; "National Stewardship Council Autry National Center Meeting of Saturday September 29, 2007", circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Stanford Alumni Association presents: 2008 Eclipse Tour Trans-Siberian Railway by Private Train information; Stanford Report September 26, 2007 with an article on NSM on page 8; Thank you note from Stanford Dean of Freshmen; Itinerary for NSM While at Stanford Sept. 13-20 2007; Emails and handwritten notes regarding the trip; Maps of the area; Invitations letters, travel plans and email correspondence regarding the trip to Stanford., circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Information regarding NSM participation as a guest lecturer in the Stanford Trans-Siberia Rail College program in 2007. Letter and email correspondence regarding the trip; Stanford Travel/Study programs booklet, 2008; Itinerary of the trip; Maps; Stanford booklets, circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - NSM Guest lecturer for conference: Colloquia International Conference on "The Mountain: in Image and Word in the English-Speaking world: the Landscape Figured and Disfigured" NSM lecture titled: The Spiritual Mountain, "Mountains have always been considered the seats of spiritual power"; Travel arrangements air and rail, to University of Toulouse. Invoice for Le Meridien, Montarnasse, travel receipts; NYT s article Cezanne's Provence, circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - TIAA Retirement information 2006-2007; "One Who Brings the Light" by NSM in World Literature Today, Nov-Dec 2007; Review of Three Plays; World Literature Today reprint from Nov-Dec 2007of article "One Who Brings the Light" by NSM (8 copies); Copies of World Literature Today Nov-Dec 2007 (2 Copies)., circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Email correspondence with Phyllis Morgan, circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Oklahoma Centennial State Poet Laureate: NSM presenter: 27 8X10 photographic prints of NSM presenting; Email correspondence regarding the event; License and release forms for event; Confirmation of the event with an attached Itinerary; Clear folder containing misc. items from the conference including an exhibit passport; ID badges for NSM and Barbara Glenn Momaday; Brochures and pamphlets for a number of booths at the event; Oklahoma City Council of State Governments calendar and special events information; Evaluation survey of CSG annual meeting; State news Vol 50, No 10 Council of State Governments Nov/Dec 2007, circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Speaker at R. Michael Kammerer, Jr's Memorial Service; Speaker List; NSM's speech included, undated (Box 3)
  - National Museum of the American Indian November 27, 2007—November 29, 2007 Vine Deloria, Jr. Native Writers Series.; Fall Calendar National Museum of the American Indian; Travel Itinerary, Travel invoices, including airline reservations, hotel invoice, correspondence regarding trip arrangements; Thank you from Anya Montiel for NSM's participation; Seven Photos of event; Confirmation from St. Regis Hotel, for Limo to Photograph Brooklin Bridge; Letter from Susie Coffin, circa 2000s (Box 3)
  - Emails regarding NSM presentation at the National Museum of the American Indian for the Vine Deloria Jr. Native Writers Series where NSM talked about his life as a writer and read from Circle of Wonder his children's book. The event took place on Nov. 28, 2007. In the folder are cards announcing the event and "thank-you" letters for his appearance., circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - Correspondence regarding reversion of rights for the man made of words. Two letters, October 26, 2007 and December 5, 2007. Address change service requested, from Macmillian, NY, circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - Invitation from Kiowa Tribe of Oklahoma in order to acknowledge NSM's designation as the Poet Laureate of the Kiowa Tribe. November 13, 2007; Program of reception at Kiowa Casino, November 20, 2007; Photo of Elizabeth Guy, signed; 12 Photos from reception; November 30, 2007, pamphlet of 100 years of change, celebrating Oklahoma Centennial Commission Exhibit, circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - Programs for an event honoring Robert H. Henry. Program reads: The United State Court of Appeals for the Tenth Circuit is Pleased to Invite You to the Investiture of the Honorable Robert H. Henry as Chief Judge of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Tenth Circuit. Folder includes invitations, programs and dinner menus from the event. Also included is "A Song of Thanksgiving for Robert Henry" by NSM and "To A Man Among Us" by NSM, undated (Box 4)
  - The Ninth Annual Border Book Festival presents A tribute to Arturo Islas, Jr. by Barbara Glenn Momaday?, undated (Box 4)
  - Invitation and response card for private Centennial reception in honor of poet Laureate NSM, November 9, 2007; Inauguration Booklet for Governor Bradford's Inaugural Prayer Service, January 7, 2007 reading by NSM; Confirmation on reservation at the Montogomery; Press release from Oklahoma Arts Council announcing NSM to receive 2007 National Medal of arts award; November 14, 2007, note congratulating NSM for receipt of National Medal of Arts, circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - DC Analysis Instructor Packet, a compendium of helpful teaching materials from A. Whitman, The Discourse Community Unit overview, An introduction to Discourse Analysis theory and method, by James Paul Gee. All materials copied on February 27, 2007, circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - Photographs of students at the Carlisle Indian Industrial School. Including: Dakota girls from Rosebud and Pine Ridge, Standing Bear and Family, Dakota boys from Rosebud and Pine ridge; Miss Fisher and Miss Bender's class, Dining hall, Dr Gavin and Miss Wilson in the infirmary, Vocational work, Bakers, Pratt and Apaches, Sioux Chiefs and Interpreters, Indian band; Negatives of a painting, The folder contains a booklet on Carlisle and a letter to NSM from Serle Chapman about NSM research on Carlisle. 16 old photographs with no labels, though they appear to also be from Carlisle., undated (Box 4)
  - Complete first draft of The Moon in Two Windows with letter to the editors. Dated December 16, 1998 (2 copies), circa 1990s (Box 4)
  - Royalty Statement, June, 2008, University of New Mexico Press; July 15, 2008, correspondence from Ford Foundation to Barbara Glenn Momaday regarding grant; July 15, 2008, correspondence from Norman Matteoni; Yellow lined writing tablet, 10 pp exterior and interior descriptions and dialogue, circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - Fortune Magazine (Dec.3 2001) featuring NSM on page 126. (2 copies), circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - Fortune Magazine (Dec.3 2001) featuring NSM on page 126. (2 copies); A letter from Fortune and a portrait of NSM, circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - Multiple copies of a writing by NSM entitled "Christmas 2006", circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - 3 copies Jemez Thunder, containing obituary of Barbara Glenn Momaday, p 3, circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - 8 Photographs, 3 identified as NSM, undated (Box 4)
  - Dissertation: Yuuyaraq (The Way of the Human Being): Yupiaq Voices in the Transmission of Religious and Cultural Knowledge by Kanaqlak (George P. Charles) from the University of California Santa Barbara, August 2000. Committee members: Ines Talamantez (chair), Dwight F. Reynolds, and Marianne Mithun., undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence January 24, 1999 to Royce Carlton regarding representation lecture engagements from NSM.; Correspondence January 24, 1999 to Helen Churko regarding NSM's speaking engagements; Manuscript The Indolent Boys by NSM, a play, circa 1990s (Box 4)
  - Bear-God Dialogue story NSM 12 pp, undated (Box 4)
  - Story—Turning Around and Yellow Grass by NSM, undated (Box 4)
  - Inaugural Poem Oklahoma 2003, copy and corrections, and reading copy by NSM, circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - Misc stories Bear-God Dialogues, undated (Box 4)
  - 2 copies Sunrise at Rainy Mountain by NSM; Explanation of The Indolent Boys by NSM; Print out of part of NSM's resume, undated (Box 4)
  - Three photographs of NSM taken by Kitty Leaken in Santa Fe, NM 2003, circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - Fortune Papers: Folder of papers from the article in Fortune magazine which NSM participated in. The papers include List of participants, Brainstorming sheets, Packets on Global Poverty Alleviation and Security Support, Bio of NSM Brainstorming packet, circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - Fortune Papers: Folder of papers from the article in Fortune magazine which NSM participated in. The papers include List of participants, Brainstorming sheets, and a Brainstorming pack, circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - Financial information regarding NSM trip to brainstorming sessions for the Fortune magazine article. Including reimbursement receipts for airline, hotel and other travel expenses, and NSM typed and handwritten ideas regarding the brainstorming activities for the event, circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - A memorial book for Lee Udall, undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, agreements and letters between NSM and Royce Carlton, Inc. which is a company or agents, managers and brokers for speakers. Booklets of information regarding the company and catalogue of speakers the company represents (including NSM) Are included in the folder as well, undated (Box 4)
  - Print reviews and articles on NSM work; Newspaper articles on NSM including the April 18th, 1999 edition of the Sunday Oklahoman which featured a story on the "The Shapers: Oklahomans Who Framed the Last 100 years" which included NSM on page 25; All articles and newspapers on NSM in this folder are from the later 1990s. The folder also includes 2 Polaroid pictures of NSM, a booklet of Al Momaday's work at St. Luke Lutheran Church, and five other pictures of NSM, circa 1990s (Box 4)
  - Papers relating to the Words Can Heal organization and its programs (NSM was an honorary Chairperson of the organization), including invitations to speak, a letter of regret that NSM could not attend an event in Colorado, and letters and material updating NSM on the progress of the organization's programs. All papers are from 2002., circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - 2003 Program Schedule for the International Achievement Summit, Washington D.C. which includes a list of honorees and past honorees (NSM is listed as a past honoree for the Pulitzer Prize who will be attending). Amongst the paperwork for the event are security clearance forms, information sheets, and letters of "thank-you" for NSM participation. Also included in the folder is Achievement Summit progress report from 2001, and Summit information from 2000., circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - Inventory list by artist describing a number of NSM artwork., undated (Box 4)
  - Information of a performance of The Indolent Boys by the Southwest Repertory Theater Company and the Museum of Indian Arts and Culture directed by Kenneth Martines on August 2002. Pictures of NSM and Barbara Glenn Momaday attending the event are included as well as "thank-you" cards and letters to NSM for attending., circa 2000s (Box 4)
  - "The Mask" by NSM (2 copies); Seven Masks by NSM (2 copies), undated (Box 4)
  - Copy of The Reporter Vol. 25 Issue 2. Annapolis, Maryland and Santa Fe, New Mexico, Spring 1999 with a story on NSM on page 5 (2 copies); Advertisement for NSM The Man Made of Words in St. Martin's Press Catalogue; A March 1999 copy of the Santa Fean Magazine with a story on NSM on page 65., circa 1990s (Box 4)